Finding Aid for Samuel Taubman papers, 1932-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Samuel Taubman papers 1932-2000
Taubman, Samuel, 1915-2004.
1 item
13 tubes
1 oversize boxes
6 linear feet
06119 Aa 2
Samuel Taubman was a 1940 University of Michigan graduate of aeronautical engineering. He served as a ground school instructor for the Civil Aeronautics Administration Aviation Ground School, worked as an engineer for Lockheed Aircraft Corporation, and later owned the National Shower Manufacturing Company in Detroit and a plant in Florida. He applied his knowledge of aircraft construction, inventing civilian products using aircraft aluminum, most notably for shower door design and manufacture. His papers include his engineering work at the University of Michigan and Lockheed, his teaching materials from Aviation Ground School, patents, designs, and photographs of his shower door designs as well as journals and drawings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Lola Taubman (donor no. 9779 ) in September 2006.
The collection is open to research.
Samuel Taubman was born in Davenport, Iowa on August 17, 1915. He graduated from Pontiac High School in Pontiac, Michigan in 1933 and attended Pontiac Junior College. He earned his Bachelor of Science degree in 1940 in aeronautical engineering at the University of Michigan. He served as a ground school instructor for the Civil Aeronautics Administration Aviation Ground School at the University of California.
He worked as an engineer at Lockheed Aircraft Corporation in the 1940s, where he designed testing equipment and methodology and also designed aircraft components. Taubman also enrolled in naval training schools in Dearborn, Michigan and Chicago, Illinois. While working for Lockheed, he enlisted in the Navy serving on the USS Randolph.
Later in his life, Taubman applied his knowledge of aircraft construction, inventing civilian products using aircraft aluminum, most notably shower door design and manufacture. In the 1950s, he founded the National Shower Manufacturing Company in Detroit and developed more than a dozen patents for his designs.
In 1980, Taubman moved his factory to Sanford, Florida, as it was no longer economically feasible to meet the new EPA pollution control requirements at the Detroit plant. He joined with a man named John Wall expanding his product line, developing products such as roll down shutters to protect windows from hurricanes, archery arrows, parts for medical devices, and window frames. National Shower continued in existence as a division, but was gradually phased out of active production in favor of other pursuits at the new facility.
In 1993, Taubman sold his interest in the factory, but remained as a consulting engineer on numerous projects including the design of an electrostatic paint line. The paint line had a long loop of chain used as a parts conveyor. Taubman calculated that the metal chain would become slack as temperatures rose from the Florida sun. He therefore added a large pulley wheel at one end of the line with hydraulic pistons which would gradually extend to take up slack in the chain. From 1993 to 2004, he also designed the interiors of Gulfstream jets built for his brother, A. Alfred Taubman. He died on December 15, 2004.
Samuel Taubman's papers include his engineering work at UM and Lockheed, his teaching materials from Aviation Ground School, patents, designs, and photographs of his shower door designs as well as journals and drawings.
The papers have been divided into six series according to the chronology of Taubman's life and work: Pontiac High School, University of Michigan, Aeronautics Administration Aviation Ground School (University of California), Lockheed Aircraft Corporation, Naval Training Schools, and National Shower Manufacturing Company and Later Work.
Subjects:
Aeronautical engineers--United States.; Aeronautics--Study and teaching.; Lockheed Aircraft Corporation.; National Shower Manufacturing Company.; Pontiac High School (Mich.); Showers (Plumbing fixtures)--Design and construction.; Taubman, Samuel, 1915-2004.; United States. Civil Aeronautics Administration.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Aeronautical Engineering--Students.
Visual Materials - Subjects
Taubman, Samuel, 1915-2004.
- Pontiac High School 1932-1933, 1958
  - Chemistry 1932 (Box 1)
  - Diploma 1933 (Box 1)
  - English (Box 1)
  - Physics (Box 1)
  - Reunion 1958 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan 1937-1940
  - Aeronautical Engineering
    - 1 1938 (Box 1)
    - 2 1939 (Box 1)
    - 3 1938 (Box 1)
    - 6 1939 (Box 1)
    - 23 1939 (Box 1)
    - 26 undated (Box 1)
    - notes
      - Aero 1-3, 6, 27, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Aero 4, 23, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - unlabeled, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Chemical Engineering 1 1937 (Box 1)
  - Chemistry 5E 1937 (Box 1)
  - Civil Engineering 2 1938 (Box 1)
  - Electrical Engineering, 2a 1938 (Box 1)
  - Engineering Mechanics
    - 1 1937 (Box 1)
    - 2 1937 (Box 1)
    - 3 1939 (Box 1)
    - 4 1938 (Box 1)
  - English
    - 2, undated (Box 1)
    - 4, undated (Box 1)
    - 6 1939 (Box 1)
    - unlabeled, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mathematics
    - 36-37 (Box 2)
    - 103 (Box 2)
    - Analytic geometry, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Mechanical Engineering
    See related materials in Drawings series
    - 2 1939 (Box 2)
    - 3 1938 (Box 2)
    - 5 1940 (Box 2)
    - 7 1939 (Box 2)
    - 15 1939 (Box 2)
  - Metal Processing
    - 2 1937 (Box 2)
    - 3 1937 (Box 2)
    - 4 1938 (Box 2)
  - Drawings 1938-1939
    - Mechanical Engineering drawings, 6 drawings (Tube 1)
    - Propeller-thrust/gradient/curves June 20, 1938, 3 drawings (Tube 2)
- University of California, Civil Aeronautics Administration, Aviation Ground School 1939-1941
  The Aeronautics Administration Aviation Ground School (University of California) series (1939-1941, 0.25 linear feet) contains teaching material such as lecture notes and exams while serving as a ground school instructor.
  - CAA exam (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Course information (Box 2)
  - Course materials, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Exams 1941 (Box 2)
  - Lectures 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Progress report on the Civil Aeronautics Authority's Pilot Training Program at the University of Michigan February 9, 1940 (Box 2)
- Lockheed Aircraft Corporation 1940-1945
  The Lockheed Aircraft Corporation series (1940-1945, 1 linear foot) includes his work at Lockheed including correspondence, patents, as well several reports from aircraft equipment tests.
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Patent designs 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - Reports and projects
    - Model-37
      - [Stabilizer tests?] 1941 (Box 2)
      - Stabilizer and other drawings 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    - Model-49
      - Analysis of down-bending failures (Box 2)
      - Operation-damage tests of proposed model-49 flap tracks undated (Box 2)
      - Operation-damage tests of proposed model-49 flap-extending cables January 7, 1943 (Box 2)
      - Stiffener stresses 1940 (Box 2)
      - Test of control-cable tension governor December 23, 1942 (Box 3)
      - Tests of ducted-skin compression panels January 24, 1944 (Box 3)
      - Tests of floor-support structure in airplane no. 1962 of model-49 series undated (Box 3)
    - Model-89
      - [Roller tests?] 1943-1944 (Box 3)
      - Tests and developments of proposed model-89 flap-system rollers and tracks 1945 (Box 3)
    - Model-349
      - Model-349 cargo floor panel tests February 2, 1943 (Box 3)
      - Pressure tests of proposed model-349 cabin windows undated (Box 3)
      - Static tests of proposed model-349 floor structure November 30, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Model XB-30
      - Preliminary design and stress analysis of main rings-front stabilizer bulkhead-ring at station 150 September 16, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Model-XP-58
      - An investigation of the crushing loads imposed on using ribs by wing flexure April 2, 1941 (Box 3)
      - Tests to determine the characteristics of double-skin type of wing construction 1941 (Box 3)
    - General and unidentified
      - The construction and operation of the Lockheed electrical system for measuring strains November 7, 1941 (Box 3)
      - Various-unidentified, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Naval Training Schools
  - Chicago, Illinois (Box 3)
  - Dearborn, Michigan, 5 folders (Box 3)
- National Shower Manufacturing Company and Later Work 1935-2000
  The National Shower Manufacturing Company and Later Work series (3 linear feet, 1 oversize box, 11 tubes of drawings, and 1 oversize model, 1935-2000) includes his work at the National Shower Manufacturing Company, including patent and trademark applications, photographs of shower door and sandblasting designs, drawings, and showroom samples and models. Taubman's later work as a consulting engineer to his Florida factory can also be found in this series including his drawings of the electrostatic paint line as well as detailed notes of his daily activities (1992-2000) as tracked in his daily planners.
  - Article about National Shower Manufacturing Company and anodizing plant 1957 (Box 4)
  - Patents and Trademarks
    - Correspondence 1952-1979 (Box 4)
    - Harness, Dickey & Pierce national infringement 1958-1961 (Box 4)
    - Bath enclosure application (case no.3) 1950 (Box 4)
    - Bath enclosure application July 21, 1950 (Box 4)
    - Towel bar application July 1950 (Box 4)
    - Trademark registration on N/S application August 2, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("National") March 29, 1955 (603,823) (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("N/S") March 29, 1955 (603,824) (Box 4)
    - Shower door handle application (case no.6) 1955 (Box 4)
    - Bath enclosure patent May 1, 1956 (2,743,795) (Box 4)
    - Shower door handle application August 31, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Patent March 5, 1957 (2,783,860) (Box 4)
    - Bath enclosure patent (Canada) May 7, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Shower door handle patent December 31, 1957 (181,822) (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("Mirrall") (Canada) September 19, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("Mirrall") (United States) September 8, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Shower door handle patent September 15, 1959 (2,904,368) (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("Spraymaster") (United States) December 15, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("Spraymaster") (Canada) May 27, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Towel bar patent June 14, 1960 (2,940,719) (Box 4)
    - Patent January 22, 1963 (3,074,077) (Box 4)
    - Patent January 29, 1963 (3,075,255) (Box 4)
    - Rolling panel closure means patent (Canada) March 10, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Trademarks ("National," "N/S") renewal May 28, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("Mirrall") renewal September 8, 1979 (684,626) (Box 4)
    - Trademark ("Spraymaster") renewal May 5, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Bath enclosure application, miscellaneous undated (Box 4)
    - Rolling panel closure means application undated (Box 4)
    - Sliding panel mountings undated (Box 4)
  - Work orders 1965-1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Daily planners
    - 1992-1994, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - 1997-2000, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - First Mirroll rolling closet door installation 1958 (Box 5)
    - Plant and anodizing plant being built 1955 (Box 5)
    - Shower doors
      - Sandblasting designs (Box 5)
      - Shower doors (and other doors), 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Unidentified parts (shower door parts?) (Box 5)
  - Samples
    - Miscellaneous brackets and metal pieces (Box 6)
    - National Shower Manufacturing Company advertising stamp (Box 6)
    - Shower door glass samples, 2 envelopes (Box 6)
    - Shower door model (Box 6)
      (oversize, stored separately)
  - Drawings
    - American Shower Door Company, Inc., instructions for completing and installing model no.500 knocked-down "American Maid" two-panel rollaway tub enclosure 1947 (Box 6)
    - Ex-cell-o Aircraft and Tool Corporation 1935 (Box 6)
    - General Motors Truck Company (Box 6)
    - Micromatic Hone Corporation (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Paint line assembly drawings
      - 400 series (17 pc.) (Box 7)
      - Accordion-shutter 1994 (Box 7)
      - Adjustable clip-forming die set 1992 (Box 7)
      - Adjustable paint-rack welding fixture 1993 (Box 7)
      - Ageing-oven cradle truck 1993 (Box 7)
      - Ageing-oven track system 1993 (Box 7)
      - Aluminum cradle 1996 (Box 7)
      - Cradle welding jig 1993, 1996 (Box 7)
      - Dryer tank system 1993 (Box 7)
      - Electrostatic-paint-line grounding system 1994-1996 (Box 7)
      - End turn 1996 (Box 7)
      - Equipment in paint building 1994, 1996 (Box 7)
      - H2SO4 platform 1993 (Box 7)
      - Hanger rod 1994-1996 (Box 7)
      - Load bar 1996-1998 (Box 7)
      - Monorail inter-building conveyor 1997 (Box 7)
      - Muntin milling head 1995 (Box 7)
      - New building 1996 (Box 7)
      - Off-line stationary hanger rod 1994 (Box 7)
      - Paint-booth grounding system 1994, 1996 (Box 7)
      - Paint line layout 1997 (Box 7)
      - Paint-line oven 1993, 1997 (Box 7)
      - Paint-rack spine 1992-1993 (Box 7)
      - Paint room and cure oven modifications 1994 (Box 7)
      - Plates and drive unit 1998 (Box 7)
      - Pre-paint treatment system 1997 (Box 7)
      - Powder booth 1991, 1993, 1996 (Box 7)
      - Powder paint line 1997 (Box 7)
      - Screen-door-assembly-bench base 1994 (Box 7)
      - Section no. 4267 shutter, 1995 (Box 7)
      - Storage rack 1992, 1998 (Box 7)
      - Sunburst window frame trimmer 1994 (Box 7)
      - Tank farm 1998 (Box 7)
      - Track support 1998 (Box 7)
      - Tube rack 1992 (Box 7)
      - Warehouse aisle dolly 1992 (Box 7)
      - Warehouse-rack arms 1998 (Box 7)
      - Wheels 1998 (Box 7)
      - Unidentified, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Parts and other drawings
      - 1947 1951
        - Buffing equipment guards December 20, 1947 (Tube 3)
        - Drill jig -- tub enc. wall channel December 15, 1951 (Tube 3)
        - Unidentified
          - August 6, 1947 (Tube 3)
          - [1947 (Tube 3)
      - 1958
        - Anodizing plant
          - Layout of dye section (Tube 4)
          - Dye or seal tank (Tube 4)
        - Shower parts design February-September 1958
          - Channel March 17, 1958 (Tube 5)
          - Division bar September 30, 1958 (Tube 5)
          - Unidentified February 10, 1958, 3 drawings (Tube 5)
        - Shower parts design October-November 1958
          - Bracket November 5, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Channel October 22, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Guide October 23, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Guide track October 14, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Jamb October 11, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Handle October 21, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Lower rail October 25, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Rail October 6, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Roller track October 7, 1958 (Tube 6)
          - Upper rail October 24, 1958 (Tube 6)
      - 1960-1961
        - Handle April 7, 1961 (Tube 7)
        - Header April 22, 1961 (Tube 7)
        - Tray March 25, 1961 (Tube 7)
        - Rail March 27, 1961 (Tube 7)
        - Splash defl. April 3, 1961 (Tube 7)
        - Three-panel folding patio door (Tube 7)
        - Tray July 14, 1961 (Tube 7)
        - Unidentified May 7, 1960 (Tube 7)
      - 1962
        - Handle September 22, 1962 (Tube 8)
        - Guide track September 24, 1962 (Tube 8)
        - T.B. fitting February 5, 1962 (Tube 8)
      - 1963
        - Guide track April 29, 1963 (Tube 9)
      - 1966
        - Howard Johnson design January 15, 1966 (Tube 10)
        - Roller track October 15, 1966 (Tube 10)
      - 1967
        - Unidentified December 4-5, 1967, 2 drawings (Tube 11)
      - 1971 1973
        - Howard Johnson design March 5, 1973 (Tube 12)
        - T.B. fitting February 12, 1971 (Tube 12)
      - Unidentified, 2 drawings (Tube 13)